from Scatteren. The standard formula is
a solveny 2 podcast for UK and European
insurance professionals. Join us as
Scatteren partner Robert Chaplan leads
conversations with industry
practitioners and explores Solveny 2
developments that matter to you.
>> Welcome to the Standard Formula podcast.
Today we'll continue our global tour of
insurance credential solveny regimes
focusing on Australia and New Zealand.
I'm Rob Chaplain and joining me is my
colleague Connor Williamson. Connor,
great to have you with us.
>> Thanks Rob, great to be here and it
should be interesting to compare the two
regimes. I also just wanted to start by
thanking our local experts Mter Ellison
in Australia and Mtor Ellison Rudwatts
in New Zealand for their input on
today's content.
>> Great. Connor, can you provide us with a
brief overview of the insurance market
in Australia, please?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So Australia's
insurance market is one of the largest
in Asia in the Asia-Pacific region. The
market's highly concentrated with a few
large players dominating both the life
and non-life sectors. The life sector
accounts for approximately 26 billion
Australian dollars in gross written
premiums while the non-life sector
represents approximately 95 billion
Australian dollars in gross written
premiums. Life insurance products are
availing term life insurance and
disability income insurance. Australian
insurers are distinctive in offering
lumpsum total and permanent disability
insurance as well as trauma and critical
illness insurance. Additionally, life
insurers in Australia provide
superanuation investment products. As
evident from the figures just mentioned,
non-life products hold a particularly
prominent share in Australia,
representing roughly 70% of life and
non-life revenue combined from 2025.
Australia's insurance frequently deal
with extreme weather events yet robust
and profitable with financial year 2025
being an especially strong year.
However, cost of living pressures,
rising business insolvenies and
accelerating climate and cyber
challenges may impact Australian risks
on a go forward basis. Distribution
channels include intermediaries, direct
sales and increasingly digital
platforms. The market is mature, well
regulated, characterized by strong
emphasis on consumer protection and
ongoing innovation. It's also worth
noting that underwriters at Lloyds are
able to underwrite Australian insurance
business pursuit to local Australian
insurance regulation. They're also able
to underwrite non-life and reinsurance
throughout New Zealand. In 2024, a
dedicated syndicate in a box was
established to focus on Australia and
New Zealand, specifically with respect
to accident, health, aviation, casualty,
construction, financial lines, and
property business. How does the
insurance market in New Zealand compare?
>> As you might expect, New Zealand's
insurance market is smaller in scale.
The market is reasonably concentrated
with a mix of local and international
insurers operating within it.
Distribution occurs through
intermediaries and direct channels and
digital adoption is steadily increasing.
However, it is less common than in
Australia. The market is undergoing
significant evolution such as moving
towards risk-based track pricing for
climate and natural hazards supported by
recent regulatory reforms designed to
enhance consumer protection and market
stability. Property and casual PNC
insurance remains the dominant sector
influenced by rising reinsurance costs
and increasing climate related risks. In
particular, the significant potential
for earthquake damage in New Zealand has
provided a challenge to the insurance
industry over the last century.
Following a series of destructive
earthquakes beginning in the 1920s, the
premiums that needed to adequately
ensure against such risks became
prohibitively expensive for the standard
commercial market. In response, the
government established the New Zealand
Earthquake Commission in the early
1940s, originally named the Earthquake
and War Damage Commission. Over time,
coverage for war damage was deemed
unnecessary and the scheme was expanded
to include certain other natural
disasters partially in response to
climate change physical impacts.
Reflecting that exa expansion, the EQC
has recently been renamed the natural
hazards commission to a currently
earthquake coverage is automatically
included when individuals purchase home
contents and fire insurance from private
insurers. As a result, up to 80% of the
economic losses resulting from an
earthquake are insured, ensuring that
resources available for reconstruction
efforts. Another unique feature of New
Zealand is the no fault accidental
injury compensation scheme administered
by the accident compensation
corporation. Since 1974, the ACC has
been the sole and compulsory provider of
accident insurance in New Zealand for
all work and non-work related personal
injuries, primarily funded for a
combination of levies and government
contributions. As a result, the market
for personal injury insurance is limited
in New Zealand. Life insurance in New
Zealand is dominated by term life
insurance with only low levels of types
of life insurance that dominate in other
markets such as investmentbased
policies. And this is largely due to the
tax treatment.
More broadly, the Austral both the
Australian and New Zealand markets are
shaped by global insurance trends and
the impact of climate change. Although
separated by distance, Australia and New
Zealand have maintained enduring
connections with the wider world through
global trade and cultural networks, all
the while preserving a strong sense of
independence. In recent times, there has
been a notable shift in their external
economic orientation, moving away from
Europe and the United States and
increasingly focusing on North and
Southeast Asia. Both Australia and New
Zealand possess abundant natural
resources but have very different
physical environments. They each also
face material risks from natural
disasters which manifest differently in
the two countries. In Australia, extreme
weather has been responsible for 4.5
billion in claims annually on average
since 2019.
And between 2020 and 2025, the insurance
market has paid out approximately 22.5
billion insurance claims for extreme
weather events, including cyclones,
bushfires, and floods. This was a 67%
increase from the preceding 5 years.
Perhaps more concerning for the
Australian insurance market is that
annual costs for extreme weather events
are projected to reach 35.2 billion per
year by 2050. The ongoing ability of
these nations and their insurance
sectors to develop effective responses
to these challenges is a testament to
their resilience. Rob, can you now give
an overview of the regulatory framework
in Australia, please?
>> Yes, of course, Connor. Australia's
insurance sector falls under a twin
peaks regulatory system that splits
financial regulation between Australia's
two largest regulatory authorities. The
Australian Credential Regulation
Authority or APA and the Australian
Securities and Investments Commission
ASICH.
APA is responsible for credential
standards, licensing and supervision in
respect to promoting financial stability
both in relation to insurers and other
financial institutions including deposit
takers.
They are a member of the international
association of insurance supervisors or
IIS.
On the other hand, ASICH oversees market
conduct and consumer protection, serving
as the conduct regulator for market
integrity and consumer protection. The
Australian Financial Complaints
Authority or AFCA
is responsible for handling consumer
disputes and is an alternative dispute
resolution forum for insurance claim
disputes.
Key legislation includes the Insurance
Act 1973 which governs the authorization
and credential supervision of general
insurers to ensure their solvency. The
life insurance act 1995 which applies to
life insurers. The Corporations Act 2001
which is overseen by ASIC and the
Insurance Contracts Act 1984 which
regulates the interpretation and
application of insurance contracts.
Recent reforms have focused on
strengthening risk management and
governance within the sector. Connell,
can you tell us please about New
Zealand's regulatory framework? Yeah, of
course. Um, and actually the first point
to understand is that New Zealand has
its own regulatory regime and that's
actually more different from Australia
than you might expect. So in New
Zealand, the Reserve Bank of New Zealand
is both the central bank and the
credential regulator for banks and
insurers with responsibility for
credential licensing, solveny standards
and ongoing supervision. You then have
the financial markets authority or the
FMA which oversees market conduct and
disclosure and conduct licensing under
the coffee reforms which I'll expand on
shortly. The R RBNZ is a member of the
AIS and the FMA is a member of IOS. In
terms of legislation, the primary
legislation in New Zealand is the
Insurance Credential Supervision Act
2010 which the RBNZ supervises from a
credential perspective and the Financial
Markets Conduct Act 2013 under which the
FMA supervises conduct. The latter was
amended by the financial markets conduct
institutions amendment act 2022
effective from March 25 which requires
financial institutions and their
intermediaries to comply with fair
conduct and associated duties in
relation to retail banking but also in
relation to consumer insurance.
The FMA also oversees New Zealand's
mandatory climate related disclosures
which have been required under the FMCA
since 2023 for large insurers i.e. those
with over $250 million New Zealand
dollars annual premium income or over 1
billion New Zealand dollars income in
gross assets. Those firms are required
to publish TCFD style climate statements
each year. Another major development
underway in New Zealand is the new
contracts of insurance act 2024 which is
due to come into for full force by
November 27 at the latest that will make
once in a generation changes to
insurance law elevating the importance
of policy holder protections
fundamentally changing duties of
disclosure and applying unfair contract
terms requirements to certain policies.
Thanks Connor. What are the requirements
for foreign insurers wishing to operate
in Australia and New Zealand?
>> Thanks, Rob. Um, so in Australia,
foreign insurers are generally required
to either establish a locally
incorporated subsidiary or operate via
an Australian branch of a foreign entity
with both options requiring
authorization from APPA and obtaining an
an Australia financial services license
from ASIC. These entities must satisfy
minimum capital requirements, maintain
robust risk management frameworks, and
ensure that key personnel meet APA's fit
and proper standards. A foreign insurer
must demonstrate that they are an
authorized insurer in their home
jurisdiction and have received the
appropriate and necessary consents, if
any, from its home jurisdiction
supervisor to establish the intu
operations in Australia. All insurers
must comply with APPA's credential
standards, including a requirement to
hold assets in Australia that exceed
their liabilities in Australia with an
appropriate buffer. A foreign branch
must also appoint an agent in Australia
who can be either an individual or a
body corporate. That being said, certain
offshore insurers are however permitted
to provide insurance in Australia
without authorization in limited
circumstances such as when providing
reinsurance or insuring high value and
unusual risks provided they meet certain
criteria.
Then turning to New Zealand, foreign
insurers are equally required to tain an
IPSA license from the RBNZ either by
establishing a locally incorporated
entity or by operating as a branch of an
overseas insurer. Recent reforms now
require non-operating holding companies
of insurers to also be approved,
enabling the RBNZ to effectively
supervise entire group supervision.
Certain overseas reinsurers and captive
insurers may be exempt from licensing if
they operate solely as reinsurers. In
New Zealand, all licensed insurers must
also meet minimum solveny and risk
management requirements. The RBNZ
evaluates the financial strength and
regulatory standard of the parent entity
as part of the licensing process.
Insurers are also subject to additional
disclosure and reporting obligations to
promote transparency and protect policy
holders. When seeking a license, an
insurer must show that it has sound
governance and ownership arrangements in
place along with an effective risk
management framework. It is also
necessary for the insurer to maintain an
approved financial strength rating and
meet the prescribed solveny requirements
ensuring an insurer can operate its
business responsibly. Additionally, the
insurer is responsible for evaluating
the suitability integrity of all
directors and senior management
including the appointed actuary. If the
insurer is established a headquartered
overseas, the RB RBNZ will also consider
the regulatory and legal environment of
the country of origin. The potential
obligation to obtain a coffee license
from the FMAA also needs to be
considered carefully for both branches
and subsidiaries as mentioned earlier.
Thanks Connor. I suggest we now turn to
the solveny regime itself and consider
the main credential capital standard for
insurers in Australia. Non-life insurers
in Australia must maintain a minimum
capital requirement or MCR to cover a
range of risks including insurance
claims, investment risks, counterparty
defaults, asset liability mismatches,
catastrophic events, and operational
errors. The absolute minimum capital for
most insurers is 5 million Australian
dollars. APPPA expects insurers to
maintain a reasonable buffer amount
above the MCR. In many respects, the
Australian credential regime for
reinsurance and insurance undertakings
is comparable to solveny 2. There are
three approaches to calculating the MCR.
The first is the prescribed method, a
riskbased factor-driven approach to
capital charges for insurance,
investment, and concentration risks with
additional capital for high exposures.
The second is the internal modelbased
method or IMB method. Insurers may use
APPA approved internal models to
estimate required capital provided the
model is robust, well-governed and
covers all material risks. The third is
the combination method. Insurers can use
the IMB method for some risks or
business segments and the prescribed
method for others with APPA's approval.
Insurers must always hold eligible
capital above the MCR.
Insurers must comply with all
governance, risk management and other
requirements which we will discuss
further shortly and additionally
reporting requirements. Material changes
to risk management strategies or
internal models must be reported to APPA
and significant changes may require
approval. It's important to note that
life insurers in Australia are subject
to a different regulatory system and are
not covered by the same requirements as
general insurers. While both life and
general insurers are dual regulated by
APPA and ASIC, they operate under
separate specialized legislation and
licensing regimes. Life insurers are
governed primarily by the life insurance
act 1995.
APPA sets different capital requirements
based on the risk profile of each
business with higher minimum capital
requirements for life insurers, a
minimum of 10 million Australian dollars
compared to the general insurance
requirement of five. Albeit otherwise
the life insurance regime is very
similar to the non-life insurance
regime. Connell, what about New
Zealand's credential capital standards,
please?
Well, New Zealand uses a riskbased
capital approach with solveny standards
set by the RBNZ. Insurers must maintain
a minimum solveny margin calculated
based on the nature and scale of their
business. The standards cover insurance
risk, asset risk, and other relevant
risks. There are of course significantly
different approaches taken in relation
to general insurers, life insuranceers.
Overall however the approach in New
Zealand is more similar to the US
riskbased capital approach than the
approach taken under Solveny 2.
The RBN zed can intervene if an insurers
solveny margin falls below the required
level including requiring remedial
action or in extreme cases restricting
business operations. Interestingly New
Zealand has the highest riskbased
capital standard in the world in
relation to seismic risk for general
insurers. The R&BN zed applies a high
catastrophic risk charge on New Zealand
licensed insurers who must hold
sufficient capital reserves or
reinsurance to cover their liabilities
for a one in 1,000year seismic event.
However, this doesn't apply to to the
natural hazards commission toku in
respect of natural disaster insurance as
this body is backed by government
guarantee rather than subject to private
insurer solveny standards. Other risks
are calibrated to a one and 200year
basis and this is far more comparable to
insurers globally which would usually be
expected to hold sufficient capital
reserves or reinsurance to cover their
liabilities for a one in 200 or one in
250ear category event. Both New Zealand
and Australia employ riskbased capital
standards to ensure the solvency.
However, New Zealand imposes more
stringent requirements for seismic
catastrophic ris risk, reflecting its
higher exposure to that type of natural
disaster. This means that while both
countries prioritize the financial
stability of insurers, New Zealand's
regulations demand greater capital
reserves specifically to address the
elevated risk of seismic events. Rob,
could you now please take us through the
corporate governance requirements for
insurers in Australia?
>> Thanks, Connor. APA requires strict
governance and risk management standards
with the board of directors of the
company ultimately responsible for sound
management. By statute, each insurer is
required to have an appointed auditor
and an appointed actury who must be
independent of each other. Key
governance requirements include specific
rules on board size and composition, an
independent chair, the establishment of
a board audit committee, a dedicated
internal audit function, appointed
auditor independence, appointed actuary,
impartiality
and policies for board renewal and
performance assessment.
Risk management standards require a
documented risk management strategy,
clearly defined managerial
responsibilities and controls, a
dedicated risk management function, and
the submission of a three-year business
plan and annual direct declarations to
APA. So, Connor, what about New Zealand?
In New Zealand, insurers must equally
have effective governance arrangements,
including a fit and proper board, clear
accountability and appropriate risk
management systems under both the IPSA
and if applicable coffee regimes.
However, there is less prescription on
board composition in than compared to
Australia. Um, but nevertheless, the
RBNZ expects insurers to demonstrate
independence and expertise particularly
for key roles such as the chief
executive, chief financial officer and
the appointed act. The latter of which
is a designated role under statute. Rob,
what are the reporting requirements for
insurers in Australia and New Zealand?
In Australia, insurers must submit
comprehensive financial and risk
management reports to APPA, including
annual and quarterly statutory returns
based on modified FRS and a certificate
from the auditor confirming the accuracy
of yearly statutory accounts.
The auditor also provides a detailed
report on the effectiveness of the
insurers's systems, procedures, and
controls, as well as any non-compliance
or issues that could impact policy
holders. The appointed actuary must
produce an annual financial condition
report and an insurance liability
valuation report or ILVR.
In New Zealand, insurers must provide
annual and halfearly financial
statements, quarterly solveny returns,
and annual actuarial reports to the RBN
zed. They must also disclose key
management changes and significant
events. Public disclosure requirements
are in place to ensure policyholder
confidence and market discipline.
Connor, how about requirements relating
to assets and liabilities under the
Australian and the New Zealand regimes?
Thanks, Rob. So, in Australia under the
supervision of APA, there is a
predominantly principle-based credential
framework and this is also the case with
respect to asset and liability rules. So
insurers are required to value assets
and liabilities largely on a fair value
basis aligned with accounting standards
with technical provisions determined
using actuarial best estimates plus risk
margins. Rather than imposing rigid
quantitive asset limits, APA relies on
strong governance requirements, board
approved investment frameworks and
riskbased capital charges to discourage
excessive concentration or inappropriate
risk takingaking. Asset liability
management is explicitly embedded within
the framework with capital requirements
sensitive to market credit liquidity and
mismatch risks.
Then looking at New Zealand equally that
also applies a fair value accounting
method for assets and applies prescribed
solveny standards to determine liability
valuation and capital requirements. The
regime combines actuarial certification,
solveny formula and supervisionary
oversight to constrain investment risk.
The approach is somewhat more structured
and formuladriven than Australia's,
particularly regarding asset eligibility
and solveny margin calculations. ALM
considerations are incorporated through
liability valuation methods, discount
rate prescriptions, and solveny stress
test calculations, though the framework
is generally less granular and less
capital sensitive to mismatch risk when
compared to Australia's regime.
>> Connor, are there any unique features in
Australia's approach to reinsurance and
risk transfer?
>> Thanks, Rob. So Australia has detailed
credential standards for reinsurance
requiring genuine risk transfer and
counterparty creditworthiness. Insurers
must report reinsurance arrangements to
APA and may only receive capital relief
if risk transfer is effective. There are
also requirements for reinsurance
recoverables and limits on exposure to
single reinsurers. In particular, in
order to have reinsurance arrangements
recognized for the purposes of
credential regulation, a general insurer
is required to enter into a legally
binding reinsurance agreement following
the two-month rule and six-month rule
for signing and stamping placing slips
and formal reinsurance contracts.
Reinsurance contracts must also be
governed by Australian law and be
subject to Australian courts the
disputes. A general reinsurer must have
a documented reinsurance management
strategy as part of its reinsurance
management framework. It must also have
sound reinsurance management policies
and procedures and clearly defined
managerial responsibilities and
controls.
Life companies are also required to
report on prescribed matters relating to
reinsurance arrangements on an annual
basis and comply with any conditions
imposed by APA in relation to approved
reinsurance or financing arrangements.
In Australia, the content of reinsurance
agreements are subject to minimal
regulatory oversight with those
agreements being governed primarily by
their terms and the common law. And what
about New Zealand's reinsurance
framework?
>> I mean, well, so the requirements are
largely similar. Um, in particular, the
regulator requires insurers to have
effective reinsurance programs with the
RBNZ assessing the adequacy and
effectiveness of risk transfer. There
are requirements for the financial
strength of reinsurers and disclosure of
reinsurance arrangements. Capital relief
is available where risk transfer is
genuine and the RBNZ monitors
reinsurance recoverables and county
partner exposures.
One area of particular interest for the
RBNZ at present is the extent to which
some New Zealand insurers rely on their
Australian parents to provide or arrange
reinsurance. The RBNZ is concerned to
ensure that the interests of New Zealand
policyh holders are appropriately
addressed, including in the event of
stress at the parent level.
>> So to close things out, Connor, how do
Australia and New Zealand's solveny
regimes compare to other international
frameworks?
>> So Australia's riskbased capital regime
is broadly aligned with international
standards such as solveny 2 and the
IIS's insurance core principles or ICPs.
The Australian framework emphasizes
market consistent valuation,
comprehensive risk coverage and strong
governance, placing Australia among the
leading jurisdictions globally. New
Zealand on the other hand, while less so
aligned with international standards at
present, are moving towards greater
alignment with international best
practices, though the current regime is
less prescriptive than solveny 2. In
September 2025, the New Zealand
government agreed to RBNZ
recommendations to reform Ipsa, which
are likely to be enacted after the
election planned in late 2026. These
reforms aim to move from the current
relatively light touch model to a more
proactive, intensive, and risk-based
one, more closely aligning New Zealand
with international practice in selected
jurisdictions, especially Europe. The
proposals are grouped into nine high
level areas of legislative change and
are designed to ensure the maintenance
of a sound and efficient insurance
sector as well as promoting public
confidence in the sector. In both cases,
international insurance groups are
likely therefore to find many of the
concepts we've discussed today familiar.
Thanks for joining me, Connor, for a
comprehensive overview of the credential
solveny regimes in Australia and New
Zealand. And thank you to our listeners.
Stay tuned for our next episode, the
last in the series, where we'll explore
major insurance markets in East and
Southeast Asia.
Thank you for joining us on The Standard
Formula. If you enjoyed this
conversation, be sure to subscribe in
your favorite podcast app so you don't
miss any future episodes. Additional
information about Scatteren can be found
at scatteren.com.
The Standard Formula is a podcast by
Scatteren, Arps, Slate, Marinflamm LLP,
and affiliates. Scatteren is recognized
for its deep experience in representing
insurance and reinsurance companies and
their advisers on a wide variety of
transactional and regulatory matters.
This podcast is provided for educational
andformational purposes only and is not
intended and should not be construed as
legal advice. This podcast is considered
advertising under applicable state laws.